Collins mss., 1926-2001 LMC 2411
Lilly Library
Collins mss.
1926-2001
Lilly Library
Collins, John W., 1912-2001
LMC 2411
35 Boxes
The Collins mss., ca. 1926-2001, consists of the correspondence, writings, photographs, albums and chess club records of influential American chess teacher John William (Jack) Collins, 1912-2001.
Access Restrictions
This collection is open for research.
Many collections are housed offsite; retrieval requires advance notice. Please make an appointment a minimum of one week in advance of your visit.
Biographical Note
Collins was born Sept. 23, 1912, in Newburgh, N.Y. His father, John Thomas Collins, a flutist and piccolo player, frequently played in John Philip Sousa's orchestra. His mother, Carolyn LaSears Collins, was a homemaker. Collins lived most of his life in New York City, becoming a chess master in the 1930s. He was a major figure in the early days of modern organized chess, serving as the first correspondence chess editor of Chess Review magazine (which later merged with Chess Life). This program laid the groundwork for the correspondence chess conducted by the United States Chess Federation. He was one of the few players who excelled nationally at both correspondence and over-the-board play, winning the U.S. correspondence championship and ranking as one of the top OTB players in the U.S. He remained an active tournament player through the 1960s, representing the United States in the first World Correspondence Chess Championship. A prolific author, he taught thousands of players through his books and articles, and was co-editor of the ninth edition of Modern Chess Openings.
Arrangement
Organized into the following series: I. Writings and Accompanying Materials; II. Professional; III. Bobby Fischer; IV. Game Records; V. Publications; VI. Correspondence; VII. Personal; VIII. Clippings; IX. Memorabilia; X. Photographs; XI. Albums and Scrapbooks; XII. Audio-Visual; XIII. Realia.
Scope and Content Note
Writings and Accompanying Materials include original drafts, typescripts, galley proofs, columns, and articles written by Collins along with related correspondence, royalty statements, contracts, and publisher agreements. The Professional series includes game submissions, income statements, awards and honors, and other materials relating to Collins' activities as Correspondence Chess Editor, chess mentor and expert.
The Bobby Fischer series includes correspondence written by Bobby Fischer to Jack and Ethel Collins; the diaries of Ethel Collins, written during Fischer's 1972 World Chess Championship victory over Boris Spassky of the USSR; and an unsigned, undated, handwritten plea for Fischer to return to playing chess professionally. The Game Records series features more than 70 years of materials pertaining to chess matches, tournaments and championships.
Correspondents in the general Correspondence series include: Lev Alburt; Emil J. Balthazar; Gigi Benson; Robert F. Brand; Robert Byrne; Irving Chernev; Church of the Larger Fellowship; E. Malcolm Cohen; John W. (Jack) Collins; Arthur Dake; E. B. Edmondson; George F. Gant; Steven Josefowicz; Kurt Landsberger; William Lombardy; Norman Monath; Milton Pauley.
Acquisition Information
Acquired: 2004, 2007
Chess clubs.; Chess --Biography.; Correspondence; Collins, John W.; Collins, John W. --Correspondence.; Fischer, Bobby, 1943-2008.; Fischer, Bobby, 1943-2008 --Correspondence.; Alburt, Lev; Alburt. Lev. Alburt's chess openings; Balthazar, Emil J.; Benson, Gigi; Brand, Robert F.; Chernev, Irving, 1900-1981; Chernev. Irving. Golden dozen (1900-1981); Unitarian Church of the Larger Fellowship; Dake, Arthur, 1910-2000; Gant, George F.; Josefowicz, Steven Zvi; Landsberger, Kurt; Lombardy, William; Monath, Norman; Pauley, Milton; Edmondson, E. B.; Adam, Edmund, 1894-1958; Adams, Weever W., 1901-1963; Broughton, Schuyler; Davis, Marna Olsen; Harrow, Brian; Humdy, Ann; Jurado, Hector; Monnier, Jacqueline Matisse, 1930--; Moskowitz, Steven; Olsen, Stan; Rees, Dick; Reinwald, Charles A.
- I. Writings and Accompanying Materials (Box 1)
  Arrangement
  Organized into the following subseries of writings by Jack Collins: My Seven Chess Prodigies; Maxims of Chess; Modern Chess Openings; Columns and Articles; Early Manuscripts; Other; and Writings by Other Authors.
  - My Seven Chess Prodigies (Box 1)
    - Correspondence with Publishers, 1973-1983; undated (Box 1)
    - Draft, Jan. 30, 1976; (2 folders) (Box 1)
    - Incomplete Index of Biographies (Box 1)
    - Index of Openings, Index of Players (Box 1)
    - Interview Transcripts (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous Magazine References on the Top Five Young Masters (Box 1)
    - Note Sheets on Young Masters (Box 1)
    - Notes and Related Materials, 1974; undated (Box 1)
    - Notes Sent to Fischer, June 29, 1974 (Box 1)
    - Royalty Statements, 1975-1978 (Box 1)
    - Young Masters Draft, 1974; (2 folders) (Box 1)
    - Various Typescript Sections, corrected (Box 1)
    - Young Masters Publisher Agreement, 1973 (Box 1)
  - Maxims of Chess (Box 1)
    - Art (Box 1)
    - Contracts and Publisher Correspondence, 1976-1977 (Box 1)
    - Draft, 1977; (2 folders) (Box 1)
    - Draft, Dec. 11, 1978 (Box 1)
    - Galley Proofs (Box 1)
    - Galley Proofs, Author's Set (Box 1)
    - Maxims (Box 2)
    - Receipts and Royalty Statements, 1978-1993 (Box 2)
    - Style Sheet and Other Notes (Box 2)
  - Modern Chess Openings (Box 2)
    - Correspondence with C.C.L.A., 1957 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence with Pitman & Sons, Ltd., 1956; undated (Box 2)
    - Correspondence with Walter Korn, 1950-1956 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence with Walter Korn, 1957-1958 (Box 2)
    - Final Page Proofs, 1957 (Box 2)
    - Page Proofs Corrections, 1957 (Box 2)
    - Recapitulation of Earnings, 1965 (Box 2)
    - Royalty Statements, 1959; undated (Box 2)
    - Typescript #1, undated (Box 2)
    - Typescript #2, undated (Box 2)
    - Typescript #3, undated (Box 2)
    - Typescript #4, undated (Box 2)
    - Typescript #5, undated (Box 2)
    - Typescript #6, undated (Box 2)
    - Typescript #7, undated (Box 2)
    - Typescript #8, undated (Box 2)
    - Typescript #9, undated (Box 2)
    - Typescript #10, undated (Box 2)
    - Typescript Material, undated; (3 folders) (Box 2)
  - Columns and Articles (Box 2)
    - Chess Life, Games by USCF Members, 1952-1954 (Box 2)
    - Chess Life, Games by USCF Members, 1954-1957 (Box 2)
    - Chess Life, Games by USCF Members, 1967-1971 (Box 2)
    - Chess Life How the Chess Openings Got Their Names Corrected Draft, undated (Box 2)
    - Chess Life Review Postal Games, Oct. 22, 1969 (Box 2)
    - Chess Movies, 1944-1949 (Box 3)
    - Chess Review Postal Games, July 11, 1957; (2 folders) (Box 3)
    - Chess Review Postal Games, Jan. 29, 1969 (Box 3)
    - Chess Review Postal Games, undated; (4 folders) (Box 3)
    - Correspondence, Chess Review Postal Games, 1970-1972 (Box 3)
    - Correspondent End Games, undated (Box 3)
    - Correspondent End Games, undated (Box 3)
    - Dictionary of American Biography, undated (Box 3)
    - Elementary Electronics En Passant, 1968-1971 (Box 3)
    - How the Chess Openings Got Their Names Allegro, undated (Box 3)
    - How the Chess Openings Got Their Names Chess Life Corrected Draft, undated (Box 3)
    - How the Chess Openings Got Their Names Chess World Uncorrected Draft, undated (Box 3)
    - Journal of Paraplegia Chess Column Notes, undated (Box 3)
    - Journal of Paraplegia Correspondence, 1951-1953 (Box 3)
    - Journal of Paraplegia Published Copies, 1951-1953 (Box 3)
    - The MCO Story Draft, undated (Box 3)
    - The MCO Story Published Version, March 1958 (Box 3)
    - Solitaire Chess, 1947 (Box 3)
  - Early Manuscripts (Box 3)
    - Around the Desk, June 15, 1937 (Box 3)
    - Big League Prospect, undated (Box 3)
    - The Cabby, March 7, 1940 (Box 3)
    - A Christmas Guest, undated (Box 3)
    - Country Cop, 1939 (Box 3)
    - Death Drops, 1944 (Box 3)
    - Football Foolishness, April 29, 1936 (Box 3)
    - Hotel Clerk, undated (Box 3)
    - A Manager's Choice, undated (Box 3)
    - A Mistake, undated (Box 3)
    - Mountain Murder, undated (Box 3)
    - Mrs. Groom's Adventure, undated (Box 3)
    - My Philosophy, Jan. 23, 1941 (Box 3)
    - No. 89655, undated (Box 3)
    - Not a Coward, undated (Box 3)
    - Pepper, undated (Box 3)
    - Pitching- Jeff Higgins, Sept.-Oct. 1939 (Box 3)
    - Political Essays and other Thoughts, 1939-1942; undated (Box 3)
    - Quoted Beliefs, undated (Box 3)
    - The Recluse Reflects, Sept. 18, 1941 (Box 3)
    - Routine Monotony, June 16, 1931 (Box 3)
    - The Ruppert Household, undated (Box 3)
    - Shorter Writings and Untitled Works, 1933; undated (Box 3)
    - The Tale of One Eight-Year Old in the Jungle, undated (Box 3)
    - Taxinter Brooklyn, Feb. 16, 1940 (Box 3)
    - Tim, undated (Box 3)
    - Turned Out, undated (Box 3)
    - War Drafts, undated (Box 3)
    - Wheelchair Detective, or The Recluse Reflects, undated (Box 3)
    - Writer's Digest Assignments, 1933-1934 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous Verse, undated (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 3)
  - Other (Box 3)
    - Chess Openings by World Champions written, 1958-1963 (Box 3)
    - Emanuel Lasker: 1868-1941, undated (Box 3)
    - A Plan to Develop Chess Ability, undated (Box 3)
  - Writings by Other Authors (Box 3)
    - Death by Santasiere, A.E., 1973 (Box 3)
    - Our Day at City Hall by Oliver Jovanovic, undated (Box 3)
- II. Professional (Box 4)
  Organized into the following subseries: Chess Club Records; Collins Kids; Game Submissions; General Business; and Other.
  - Chess Club Records (Box 4)
    - A Lecture at the Brooklyn Chess Club, Jan. 11, 1947 (Box 4)
    - Brooklyn Chess Club, 1946-1948 (Box 4)
    - Brooklyn Chess League, 1934-1937 (Box 4)
    - "Caissa's Clarion," Brooklyn Chess Club Bulletin, 1947 (Box 4)
    - "Caissa's Clarion," Brooklyn Chess Club Bulletin, 1948 (Box 4)
    - Hawthorne Chess Club, Attendance and Dues, 1931-1939 (Box 4)
    - Hawthorne Chess Club, Correspondence, 1932-1937 (Box 4)
    - Hawthorne Chess Club, Constitution, Minutes and Matches, 1931-1933; undated (Box 4)
    - Manhattan Chess Club, 1970-1978; undated (Box 4)
    - Marshall Chess Club, 1940-2000; undated (Box 4)
    - Metropolitan Chess League, 1952-1954; 1962 (Box 4)
    - Ventnor City Invitation, 1939; 1940 (Box 4)
  - Collins Kids (Box 4)
    - 1984 Chess Festival, Kiamesha Lake, July 16-20 (Box 4)
    - Chess Saga, 1986 (Box 4)
    - Chess Saga vs. Icelandic Youth Team Programs, 1990 (Box 4)
    - Amateur Team Championship Results and Honors, 1996 (Box 4)
    - The Collins Kids Clarion Vol. III, Spring 1997 (Box 4)
    - CK vs. Harvard and Rockefeller, New York, 1978 (Box 4)
    - CK vs. Icelandic and Israeli Youth Teams, 1984; (2 folders) (Box 4)
    - CK vs. Icelandic Youth and Ethel Collins Memorial Tournament, June-July 1996 (Box 4)
    - CK vs. West Point Cadets, Apr. 17, 1982 (Box 4)
    - Copies of Logo Design (Box 4)
    - Ethel B. Collins Memorial Tournament, March 1994 (Box 4)
    - Proposed CK vs. Icelandic Kids, New York, 1978-1979 (Box 4)
    - Receipts (Box 4)
    - United States Chess Federation Affiliate Certificates, 1999; 2000 (Box 4)
    - Other, 1972-2001; undated (Box 4)
  - Game Submissions (Box 4)
    - 1938-1969 (Box 4)
    - 1970-1971 (Box 4)
    - 1972 (Box 4)
    - 1973, 1976; undated (Box 4)
  - General Business (Box 4)
    - Address Book #1 (Box 4)
    - Collins' Income, 1945-1971 (Box 4)
    - Collins' Income, 1973 (Box 4)
    - Contact Information (Box 4)
    - Jack's Inventories (Box 4)
    - Other Telephone and Address Books (Box 4)
    - Phone Book (Box 4)
    - Rolodex, A-G (Box 4)
    - Rolodex, B-H (Box 5)
    - Rolodex, H-S (Box 5)
    - Rolodex, I-R (Box 5)
    - Rolodex, S-Z (Box 5)
    - Rolodex, unsorted (Box 5)
  - Other (Box 5)
    - Awards and Honors (Box 5)
    - Biographical Materials on Chess Players, A-G (Box 5)
    - Biographical Materials on Chess Players, H-K (Box 5)
    - Biographical Materials on Chess Players, L-Z (Box 5)
    - Chess Bios (Box 5)
    - Chess Life Data (Box 5)
    - Collins and Dunst Correspondence Chess Course, 1945; undated (Box 5)
    - Collins' Exhibit, World Chess Hall of Fame, 2001 (Box 5)
    - Complete Ableware Catalog, JWC Feature, 1995 (Box 5)
    - David Feldman, Early Prodigious Achievement, 1975 (Box 5)
    - Interviews with Collins (Box 5)
    - JWC Biographical Material (Box 5)
    - The Lincoln Hilton, undated (Box 5)
    - Logo Prints (Box 5)
    - United States Chess Federation, 1975-1992 (Box 5)
    - United States Chess Federation Forms and Papers (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 5)
- III. Bobby Fischer (Box 5)
  Scope and Contents
  Note: the bulk of the correspondence in this series are letters written by Bobby Fischer to John and Ethel Collins.
  - Correspondence (Box 5)
    - Collins, Ethel, 1976-1979 (Box 5)
    - Collins, Ethel and John, 1958-1967; undated (Box 5)
    - Collins, John, 1959-1982; undated (Box 5)
    - Edmondson, Ed, Oct. 29, 1969 (Box 5)
    - Koch, Edward I., Feb. 16, 1978 (Box 5)
    - Regarding Schuyler Broughton, 1976-1988 (Box 5)
  - Bobby Fischer Game Records (Box 5)
    - 1953-1961, undated (Box 5)
    - Copies of Games, 1971; undated (Box 5)
    - "Game of the Century" Score Sheet and Analysis, Oct. 17, 1956 (Box 5)
    - Score Sheets and Notes, 1958-1964; undated (Box 5)
    - Unidentified Clipping, undated (Box 5)
  - Memorabilia (Box 5)
    - World Championship, 1972 (Box 5)
    - Ethel Collins' Diaries from World Championship, 1972 (Box 5)
  - Other (Box 5)
    - Blank Postcard Given to Jack from Bobby (Box 5)
    - Clippings World Championship, 1972 (Box 5)
    - Clippings and Articles (Box 5)
    - Clippings and Notes, Bobby Fischer and Iceland (Box 5)
    - District Court Case, Fischer vs. Darrach, Dec. 1975 (Box 5)
    - Plea for Fischer to Return to Chess, undated (Box 5)
    - "The Role of Bobby Fischer as a Cold War Symbol", Mar. 9, 1992 (Box 5)
- IV. Game Records (Box 6)
  Contains general game records covering the arc of Collins' career. Game records for Bobby Fischer are in the Bobby Fischer series.
  - Anderssen's Games, Opening Index, undated (Box 6)
  - Assorted Problems: Moves in 5-16 Moves, 16 Problems-No Solutions (Box 6)
  - Belgrade, 1964 (Box 6)
  - Benoni, La Defense Benoni et La Defense Benoni Moderne, undated (Box 6)
  - Championnat de France, 1963 (Box 6)
  - Collins' Games, 1932-1940 (Box 6)
  - Collins' Games, 1938-1970; undated (Box 6)
  - Collins' Games, 1941-1950 (Box 6)
  - Collins' Games, 1951-1960 (Box 6)
  - Collins' Games, 1955-1972; 1976 (Box 6)
  - Collins' Games, 1956 (Box 6)
  - Collins' Games, 1961-1999 (Box 6)
  - Collins' Games, 1969 (Box 6)
  - Collins' Games, 1971 (Box 6)
  - Collins' Games, undated (Box 6)
  - D. Byrne Matches, 1967-1968 (Box 6)
  - Compiled Budapest Defense, Josef Staker and Alan Glasscoe, 1979 (Box 6)
  - European Tournaments, 1899-1904 (Box 6)
  - European Tournaments, 1909-1921 (Box 6)
  - European Tournaments, 1923-1936 (Box 6)
  - Games Annotated by Collins, 1945-1949; undated (Box 6)
  - Games Annotated by Collins, 1948-1950; undated (Box 6)
  - Games Annotated by Collins, 1950-1952 (Box 6)
  - Hermann Helms vs. Louis J. Wolff, February 1908 (Box 6)
  - Inventories, 1953-1962 (Box 6)
  - JWC Annotations on Saul Rubin's Games, Apr.-May 1956 (Box 6)
  - JWC Weekly Planners, 1978-1981 (Box 7)
  - JWC Weekly Planners, 1982-1984 (Box 7)
  - JWC Weekly Planners, 1985-1987 (Box 7)
  - JWC Weekly Planners, 1988-1990 (Box 7)
  - JWC Weekly Planners, 1991-1993 (Box 7)
  - JWC Weekly Planners, 1994-1995 (Box 7)
  - Kresse vs. Austin Special Leadership, Notes by JWC, 1939 (Box 7)
  - Log Cabin Chess Club, U.S.C.F., Seeded Championship, Aug. 1959 (Box 7)
  - Lombardy Games, undated (Box 7)
  - Marshall Championship, Collins vs. K. Messerschmitt, Budapest Defense, Mar. 2, 1940 (Box 7)
  - Match with Marshall, 1907 (Box 7)
  - My Games of Chess by John Collins, Book I, 1932-1937 (Box 7)
  - My Games of Chess by John Collins, Book II, 1937-1938 (Box 7)
  - Opening Options by John Collins, Sept. 21, 1948 (Box 7)
  - Photostats Published by the Dutch Chess Center, 1952-1954 (Box 7)
  - Postal Instruction Games, 1914; 1950; 1957-1967 (Box 7)
  - Postal Instruction Games, 1968-1976; 1980 (Box 7)
  - Postal Instruction Games Annotated by Collins, 1951-1952 (Box 7)
  - Records of Collins' Prize Winnings, 1948-1952; undated (Box 7)
  - Reshevsky Memorial Tournament, Rounds 1-7, 1992 (Box 7)
  - Santasiere Games, 1971 (Box 7)
  - Selected Games by JWC, undated (Box 7)
  - Seventh Midwest Open and Nebraska State Chess Championship, Sept. 1957 (Box 7)
  - To Collins from Lombardy, Christmas, 1994 (Box 7)
  - U.S. Chess Championship, 1966-1967 (Box 7)
  - 1959-1963 (Box 7)
  - Untitled, January 1979 (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 7)
- V. Publications (Box 8)
  Arranged alphabetically by title, then oversized.
  - 14th U.S. Jr. Chess Championship & 60th U.S. Open Chess Championship, 1959 (Box 8)
  - 59th Annual U.S. Open Chess Championship, Rochester, MN, 1958 (Box 8)
  - Ableware Homeware Catalog (Collins Feature), 1995 (Box 8)
  - Absolute Chess by Weaver W. Adams, 1959 (Box 8)
  - All Games from the XXIII U.S.S.R. Chess Championship, 1956 (Box 8)
  - All Games from the Carlsbad International Chess Congress, 1929 (Box 8)
  - All Games from the New York International Chess Congress, 1927 (Box 8)
  - American Chess Bulletin Vol. 36, No. 4, Jul.-Aug., 1939 (Box 8)
  - Chess, 1936; 1939; 1958 (Box 8)
  - Chess Charts Issue No. 2, April, 1941 (Box 8)
  - The Chess Correspondent Vol. XXV, Nos. 5 and 6, 1952 (Box 8)
  - Chess Endings from Modern Master Play Jacques Mieses, 1901 (Box 8)
  - Chess is an Art by Richard Kujoth, 1955 (Box 8)
  - Chess Life, 1953; 1961; 1963 (Box 8)
  - Chess Life Vol. 38, No. 8, August 1953 (Box 8)
  - Chess Life Vol. 41, No. 6, June 1986 (Box 8)
  - Chess Life Vol. 46, No. 5, May 1991 (Box 8)
  - Chess Life, 2000-2002 (Box 8)
  - Chess Life Proof Copy, March 2002 (Box 8)
  - Chess Life and Review and, May; August, 1978 (Box 8)
  - Chess Monthly Vol. 62, No. 8, November 1997 (Box 8)
  - Chess Pie, 1922; 1927 (Box 8)
  - Chess Pie No.3, 1936 (Box 8)
  - Chess Review, October 1952 (Box 8)
  - Chess Review, February 1954 (Box 8)
  - The Chess Review, December 1938 (Box 8)
  - The Chess Weekly Vol. 11, No. 18, March 27, 1909 (Box 8)
  - A Course in the Elements of Modern Chess Strategy Reinfeld and Green, Lessons I-V, 1935 (Box 8)
  - A Course in the Elements of Modern Chess Strategy Reinfeld and Green, Lessons VI-XII, 1936 (Box 8)
  - David Bronstein's Best Games of Chess by Larry Evans, Limited Ed. No.2, 1944-1949 (Box 8)
  - Empire Chess Vol. VI, No. 1, Winter 1986 (Box 8)
  - Finals and Semi-finals of the Manhattan and Marshall C.C. Championships, 1956-1957 (Box 8)
  - Fred Reinfeld Limited Editions, Vol. V, Botvinnik's Best Games, Part I, 1927-1934 (Box 8)
  - Fred Reinfeld Limited Editions, Vol. X, Ventnor City Tournament, 1939 (Box 8)
  - Fred Reinfeld Limited Editions, Vol. VII, Semmering-Baden Tournament, 1937 (Box 8)
  - Fretta-Blad T.R., 1980; 1982; 1983 (Box 8)
  - Het Eindspel No. 9, Dr. M. Euwe, 1951 (Box 8)
  - Instructive and Practical Endings from Master Chess Reinfeld, Lessons II-IV, 1937 (Box 9)
  - International Chess Tournament, Carlsbad, Bohemia, Aug.-Sept., 1911 (Box 9)
  - Materials about Iceland, 1985-1987 (Box 9)
  - Milwaukee, 1957, Edited by Jack Spence, 1958 (Box 9)
  - Milwaukee Chess Championships, New Western and North Central, 1959 (Box 9)
  - Modern Iceland, Special Issue: Centuries of Chess, 1987 (Box 9)
  - National Geographic Vol. 172, No. 2, February 1987 (Box 9)
  - New Ideas in Old Settings: The Caro-Kann Defense by Warren H. Goldman, 1958 (Box 9)
  - New Jersey Open Chess Championship Compiled by Robert Durkin, 1959 (Box 9)
  - Newsletters, 1966-1993 (Box 9)
  - Principles of Strategy in the Game of Checkers Louis C. Ginsberg, 1932 (Box 9)
  - Quest, March 1987 (Box 9)
  - Roman Pelts Instructional Materials (Box 9)
  - Russian Works, 1947; 1951 (Box 9)
  - Selected Games from the 58th U.S. Open Chess Championship, 1957 (Box 9)
  - Selection of Games from the San Diego Open, August, 1956 (Box 9)
  - Simple Chess by Weaver W. Adams, 1946 (Box 9)
  - Simple Chess by Weaver W. Adams, Revised, 1958 (Box 9)
  - Skakfelagsbladid 9-21 mars, 1988 (Box 9)
  - Some Facts about Iceland for Ethel Collins, PC Globe, Inc., 1990 (Box 9)
  - Les Tableaux Echiqueens, A. Garreau, [1966] (Box 9)
  - Tartakower Memorial Chess Congress, Detroit, 1956 (Box 9)
  - Temas XXV, No. 292, Mayo, 1975 (Box 9)
  - TWA Ambassador, Mayo 1980 (Box 9)
  - U.S. Chess Championship and 5th Rosenwald Trophy Tournament, 1958-1959 (Box 9)
  - U.S. Chess Saga, 1984-1990 (Box 9)
  - Ventnor City International Masters Tournament, 1945 (Box 9)
  - Vienna International Tournament by Larry Evans, 1948 (Box 9)
  - Vim and Vigor, Fall 2000 (Box 9)
  - World Championship Candidates Tournament, 1953 (Box 9)
  - Miscellaneous Printed (Box 9)
  - Chess Archives Dr. M. Euwe, 1965-1966; (binder) (Box 9)
  - Life Magazine The Deadly Gamesman (Bobby Fischer), Nov. 12, 1971; (2 copies) (Box 35)
  - America (Russian language), includes "A Passion for Chess" article on Jack Collins, 1978 (Box 10)
- VI. Correspondence (Box 10)
  Organized alphabetically by last name of the correspondent. Correspondence from Bobby Fischer is located in the Bobby Fischer series.
  - A-B (Box 10)
  - C (Box 10)
  - Collins, John W. (Box 10)
  - D-E (Box 10)
  - F-I (Box 10)
  - J-L (Box 10)
  - M-O (Box 10)
  - P-S (Box 10)
  - T-U (Box 10)
  - U.S. Chess Federation: Instructions and Introductory Letters, 1952-1953 (Box 10)
  - V-Z (Box 10)
  - Unidentified, 1946-1999 (Box 10)
  - Correspondence re: Collins Kids and Chess as an Amateur Sport, 1978 (Box 10)
  - Framed Letter from Wilhelm "William" Steinitz to J. Spence, August 31, 1895 (Box 31)
- VII. Personal (Box 10)
  - Carolyn LaSears Boyd Collins Biographical Material (Box 10)
  - Collins' Family Tree (Box 10)
  - Collins' Genealogy Information (Box 10)
  - Custom-Made Tricycle, 1966-1967 (Box 10)
  - Dad and Mother's Birth Certificates (Box 10)
  - Dad's Army Papers, 1899; 1930; undated (Box 10)
  - Estate of John W. Collins (Box 10)
  - Framed JWC Memorabilia (Box 10)
  - Grandfather Collins' Papers, 1873-1903 (Box 10)
  - Henry E. Ecktrom's Will and Death Certificate, 1964 (Box 10)
  - JWC Letter to President F.D. Roosevelt, May 15, 1941 (Box 10)
  - John and Ethel Collins' Household Inventory, undated (Box 10)
  - John W. Collins Composition Book (Box 10)
  - John and Ethel Collins' Household Inventory (Box 10)
  - Medicaid Application, January 12, 2001 (Box 10)
  - Memorial of Ethel B. Collins for John W. Collins, May 25, 1993 (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 10)
  - Mother's Keepsakes (Box 10)
  - New York Society for Ethical Culture, June-July, 1981 (Box 10)
  - Personal Effects (Box 10)
  - Polka Brilliante, Piccolo Solo Played by John T. Collins (Box 10)
  - Sheet Music, Words and Music by Jack W. Collins, undated (Box 10)
  - Sousa Band Society News, September 1977 (Box 10)
  - Will and Bequeath of Louis J. Wolff, 1985-1986 (Box 10)
  - Will of Alexander Meyer, March 21, 1990 (Box 10)
  - JWC Memorial Guestbook (album) (Box 10)
- VIII. Clippings (Box 11)
  - Allegro, May 1975 (Box 11)
  - Articles about JWC (Box 11)
  - Chess, 1939 (Box 11)
  - Chess, 1941 (Box 11)
  - Chess, 1944 (Box 11)
  - Chess, 1945 (Box 11)
  - Chess, 1946 (Box 11)
  - Chess, 1947 (Box 11)
  - Chess, 1948 (Box 11)
  - Chess, 1949 (Box 11)
  - Chess, 1940s (Box 11)
  - Chess, 1950 (Box 11)
  - Chess, 1951 (Box 11)
  - Chess, 1952 (Box 11)
  - Chess, 1953 (Box 11)
  - Chess, 1954 (Box 11)
  - Chess, 1955 (Box 11)
  - Chess, 1956 (Box 11)
  - Chess, 1957 (Box 11)
  - Chess, 1958 (Box 11)
  - Chess, Cazenovia, 1958 (Box 11)
  - Chess, Rochester, 1958 (Box 11)
  - Chess, 1965; 1967 (Box 11)